<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A dissection of all governments: or, An answer to a pamphlet, entituled, The priviledges of the people, or, Principles of common right and freedome, briefly laid open and asserted in two chapters, &amp;c. By W.J.</title>
            <author>W. J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 31 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A87503</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99862864</idno>
  <idno type="VID">115042</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240949843</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J48</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E545_23</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202647</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99862864</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-99862864e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A87503)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115042)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 84:E545[23])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A dissection of all governments: or, An answer to a pamphlet, entituled, The priviledges of the people, or, Principles of common right and freedome, briefly laid open and asserted in two chapters, &amp;c. By W.J.</title>
                  <author>W. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 13, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the yeer. 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: Warr, John.  The priviledges of the people.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "March. 1st 1648".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Warr, John. --  Priviledges of the people.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Representative government and representation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Political science --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115042:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115042:1"/>
            <p>A DISSECTION OF ALL GOVERNMENTS: <hi>OR,</hi> An Answer to a Pamphlet, entituled, THE PRIVILEDGES OF THE PEOPLE, OR, Principles of Common Right and Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, briefly laid open and asserted in two Chapters, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. J.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the Yeer. 1649.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:115042:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115042:2"/>
            <head>A Dissection of all Governments.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Shall not undertake in so short a time as is necessary for the confutation of a Pamphlet, to tire my selfe and my Reader too with a punctuall Answer line by line to his Paper entituled, <hi>The Priviledges of the People, or Principles of common Right and Freedome briefly laid open and asserted in two Chapters,</hi> since I know that such an Answer must exceed the measure of a Pamphlet; and therefore I shall only anatomize all Governments as briefly and plainly as I can, that all people may have both the leisure and capacity of being my Judges, without the trouble of searching other books for the truth of my Citations.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>THat Kings out of vanity and self-interest have frequently misapplyed that power intrusted to them by God and man, I shall not at all deny (though that is not to be applyed to our late renowned King neither) but if this be a rule for the abolishing of Monarchy, it will be as infallible for the dissolution of all Government, since that ambition, avarice, revenge, and all other imperfections in our natures, which may be assigned to Kings, as causes of misgovernment, are upon the same account to be expected from the naturall or accidentall corruption of every particular person in a number of Rulers, when they once come to the power of throwing off their disgui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ses, and securely prosecuting their own interests. And if every private man be subject to the same corrupt will that a King is, what will this amount to in a multitude of Governours, when every one hath a distinct self-interest (as much as a King) to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for, not only of his own Family, but of all others his friends and allies, whose fortunes must be made up out of the publique
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115042:3"/>stock, besides the prejudice (if not ruine) of those particular fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies that shall happen to have any controversies with them or any of their dependents, from the highest to the lowest. And what a transcendent tyranny this must necessarily be, when every Member hath the power of a King, to delay the justice of the poor people (if not totally to obstruct it) I need go no further for an example then this present Parliament, which was a free e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of as many supposed Patriots (as least enemies to Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative) as ever met together, and yet how soon, and to what an excesse of corruption, faction, and arbitrary power they grew (even in those things they had formerly complained of) is too evident to need any proof. There are too many wofull examples of people imprisoned without hearing for Delinquents, upon the least malicious suggestion or misinformation of their factious neighbours (from whom no quiet people can be free) that have not so much as in their language appeared for the King or his Party; Besides the tyring of the poorer sort with a chargeable attendance, to the losse of their rights, for want of money or friends, or else because they must not be heard against the well-effected, that is, those of their faction and kindred. And the fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent bespeaking of Parliament-men for friends in businesses, be they right or wrong, who were quickly perswaded not only to do courtesies in that kind for their dependents, but for one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, and the active malice of one enemy to a poor Plaintife that can propose any thing to cause debates, and by consequence delay (which is the inseparable infirmity of all great Councells) shall (with the help of his faction) at any time hinder the course of Justice, if by an unjust sentence they do not rob men of their rights. To these naturall (and notorious known corruptions) both in this, and all other great Councells, bribery may very well be added, since I think it will not be denyed but the major part of mankind (if they be not positively dishonest) are to be obliquely led unto it by hope, fear or some error of judgement, and if so, what a fine game have the dishonester (who must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessarily be the craftier sort) to play, amongst a company of more plainde-aling, honest, foolish and cowardly people; we have found to our cost how well they can inrich themselves, and upon what really specious pretences, at least such as appear so to
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115042:3"/>the humours of those they have to deal withall. But it will be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged that (though a body once corrupt is not to be restored) as appears by the foulnesse of our present Parliament after so many purges; yet most of the foregoing inconveniences are to be prevented by due Elections and often changing of the Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sentatives. To this I shall give a more satisfactory Answer in it's proper place in the following Chapter. But for the present I shall only say, that I am confident that there will never be a more free and impartiall Election of any Representative then was original<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of this Parliament, at least whilst there is any Army in the Kingdome; And yet we see how they have proved. And to say truth there is no Government in the world that is not subject to much depravation; but since the worst of Governments is a shelter from the storme of confusion, (that many headed tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that bears down all property before it,) we ought undoubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edly to chuse that least of evills which is freest from a generall oppression, and is the best established bay or protection from that universall inundation of ruine, called the liberty (though not the property) of the people, to do what they list, and be Judges not only of their own established Judges, upon the suddain moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any springing faction amongst them, but of all controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies amongst themselves, according to the strength of their seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall factions necessarily growing from the inconstancy, and varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of their particular opinions and interests.</p>
               <p>But to conclude my Answer to this first Chapter, I think I need no farther inlarge my self; if it be granted that the avarice of one Family with its Councellors, allies and dependents of all kinds, may better be satisfied at the publique charge of a Kingdome, then of four hundred interests with the same apurtenances; and if it be as certain that ten men may resolve as wisely of any busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse as any number whatsoever, (especially in the administrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Justice according to known rules,) no doubt, for the ease of the Subject in their dispatch, the convenience is so great as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most to ballance all other discommodities; besides if they must be bribed, lesse money will serve, as we have shewed, and they will in time be glutted, and if it be no lesse clear in poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique affairs that (for the secret and suddain dispatch of them) the number must be reduced to a few, as appears by the State
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115042:4"/>Committee at Darby-house, who have a greater trust reposed in them, and do daily act things of greater consequence to the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome (without giving any account of them) then all the great Councell besides: and if the rule be the same for the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of an Army by a Generall, who is an absolute Monarch, with such of his Councell as he pleaseth only to call, and that the maintenance of all Lawes and Rights must depend upon this or some such like arbitrary power, as too sadly now appears; then I say we may clearly and safely conclude, that it holds throughout for a certain truth, that a perpetuall Monarchy though with the worst of Kings, is a more easie &amp; commodious Government, then a perpetuall Parliament, or Representative, and by consequence elective and alterable, Kings are by the same measure to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred before a changeable Representative or Parliament. Now whether an hereditary or elective Monarchy be to be preferred, or a mixt Government, will properly be the subject of my Answer to the following Chapter, being the last, and intituled,</p>
            </div>
            <div type="chapter">
               <head>Of the Peoples right in the choice, change or regulation of Government; together with the originall of Kingly power, and other forms of Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment.</head>
               <p>TO overthrow the specious structure of this Title and follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Chapter, appearing so beautifull and strong, but tending indeed to the ruine of all Order and Government, and by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of mankind, I must begin with the rottennesse of its foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation, and shew how pernitious and false that Maxime, which hath so fair an outside, is, that all Government are fundamental<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly seated in the people, which I take to be the ground of all the following assertions, and, next to self-interest, the sad cause of all the late proceedings in this Kingdome, and therefore to clear it to all impartiall people, I shall begin first with the Will of God shewed in his first foundation for the good of man, directly op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potsie to this principle, though he hath permitted a kind of forms of Government since, as he hath allowed other miseries and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fusions to fall upon us for our chastisement, the better to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince our extravagant fancies and inclinations, and reduce us to what he first thought fit for us; and next I shall make it appear in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115042:4"/>reason impossible to be a wholsome or a true Maxime. And to begin with the Creation of the world, I think no man will deny, but that it was as consistent with Gods insinite goodnesse, and as easie for him, to have created a world of people at once, as one sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle <hi>Adam,</hi> had he not foreseen the turbulent factiousnesse and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>constancy of mans nature, tending to the alteration of all good things, and the destruction of one another; and therefore to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent this confusion till their sins should more justly draw it upon them, be made one single man the possessor of the whole world, that (besides that Princely right) he might be the better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in the Monarchicall Government of the people that were to spring from him, by being a Father to them both in nature and experience. Behold here (all ye seekers of rapine and confusion under the shadow of liberty) this great and primitive work of your Creator for man before he had offended him. Wherein you so evidently perceive (not by his words in Parables) but the most universall of his actions, that this God of order in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended man for his Image as well in Monarchicall Government a<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> in his personall resemblance. And (if we beleeve that what he in his providence hath most generally thought fit in all Ages, ought conscientiously to be so received by us) it is as notorious that the Fathers of the people after <hi>Adam,</hi> from whom so many Nations sprung, were absolute Monarchs; and that the generality of Governments even to this day have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued the same, except when he was pleased to scourge the world with the conquests and oppressions of the Romanes, or would shew his people the effects of their levity, presumption, and crimes. Certainly any man that believes that the fall of a leafe is not without his particular providence, must necessarily be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by these evidences, especially when he hath in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture given even to heathen Kings, as <hi>Cyrus</hi> and others, the attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute of his Annointed, which is a marke of his favour that will hardly be found for any other Government: But since all this will be nothing to those of our present Rulers, that believe the Bible to be but a good Romance, as most of them have shewed by their actions, and some by their expressions, it will be neces<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sary to offer at a little reasoning with them, the nature and diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence between the elective and changeable Government they
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115042:5"/>aime at, with the power of the people therein, and a hereditary Monarchy.</p>
               <p>And the better to make good my assertions by a chain of unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niable consequences; I must begin with the originall necessity of order and superiority; since it must be granted that the very word Government (in the best sence) must be an insupportable found to the freedom of mans nature, if we could live without it. But since men were made with minds as different as their faces, and that self-love and interest is the most naturall and predomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of all mans thoughts &amp; inclinations, and inseparable from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which no other affection in us is, it must certainly follow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Government, that the good and ill natures, more or lesse, must one with another be subject to murder, rob, deceive, and prejudice one another in all kinds that they can; for the ill dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>positions would do it for their recreations, as well as interest; and the good in their own defence, as finding so many oppressors, and by consequence having reason to suspect all, would be apt to strike first, to prevent the blow of another; and must, being rob'd of all, do it for their sustenance, and so, through suspition and hatred springing from necessity and perpetuall provocations, and the habite and fashion of doing ill, the best and worst would grow alike, were they not limited by Religion and Government; And so every mans neighbour would be as great a tyrant and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to his property as can be imagined. For this reason, as my adversary hath very well observed, were Kings found necessary by our Ancestors to protect them from these violences; As <hi>Tully</hi> (whom he cites) hath very well expressed, though <hi>Tully,</hi> being a Heathen, rather supposed them to have been elected, then as I have express'd, according to holy Writ, hereditary. But because, in the very next line, our opposite gives us so proper an example of the corruption of an elective King, I shall give it you in his own words. (We have an instance out of <hi>Herodian Clio,</hi> where the Medes revolting from the Assyrians chose one <hi>Detoces</hi> for their King, a man of supposed strictnesse and equity in preventing dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders and abuses amongst them. But this remedy in time proved as bad as the disease; so that the people were forced to seek pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection under severall Rulers which they missed under one.) These are his words. But he tells us not whether they found it
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115042:5"/>under severall Rulers, nor how long they injoy'd it. But, for <hi>Dei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oces</hi> whom they chose, I suppose they thought him a man of as much integrity as <hi>Cromwell</hi> in the Armies opinion; and yet power corrupted him; and that a number of four hundred must have more corruption amongst them then can be in one, though the worst of men, I think I have already sufficiently proved. But to proceed to the nature of elections in generall, though we have found a great deal of calmnesse in them here, by reason that a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament-man was not a considerable preferment whilst they were Representors only, and not Judges of the peoples grievances, yet they are notoriously known to be fountaines of as great corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, faction, confusion and bloudshed as can be in the world; especially in the choice of Kings, without there be a perpetuall standing Army to make an arbitrary decision of such controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sies; and whether that remedy be as bad as the disease I need not at all dispute. But otherwise, the chargeable preparation of their factions to come glorious and strong to the place of Election, with the maintenance of them there, proves an expence and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice to their private fortunes, that must be made good out of the publique stock when they are chosen; and what clashing there is of the pretenders to a Government with their friends and followers at such a time, hath been so evident in Poland and other places, that we may well conclude, that every one of them threatens the greatest miserie that can happen to a Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, I mean a civill War: and how few of these Rulers prove the men of merit they at first pretended to be, we have too many examples, besides the forementioned <hi>Deioces:</hi> and indeed it is not to be expected from them, because besides the charges of getting to their places, they are to provide, whilst they may, for the perpetuall support of their families in that height of luxury that their greatnesse hath raised them unto; and if we consider our Elections of Parliament-men in England, we shall find, that one is chosen for placing some few gifts well, another because he keeps a good house, a third, because he is a good hypocrite, and preaches well; a fourth, because he is rich, a fift, because he can be drunk with all his neghbours, a sixt, meerly because he is a foole, and therefore thought an honest man; but the greater part because they are of the kindred or faction of those that have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115042:6"/>then the chiefe power in the Nation, whilest the more learned and modest sort that despise the vanity of popularrity and turbulent factiousnesse, and apply themselves to the Phylosophicall conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of vertues out of fashion, are neither understood, nor so much as thought of; and that this ever hath been, and ever will be so, is as certaine, as that the greatest part of the world, especi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally of the common people, are fools. And a changeable Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative chosen by, and framed out of the common people, as they are for the most part like to be, will be the same, if not a worse burthen then I have already proved a perpetuall Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: But to begin with what is to be said in their behalf, all that I know of it is, that they will not have time to grow into factions, and shuffle the Knaves together, nor dare they be so dishonest, because their reigne is but short, and they may be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to an account for their misdemeanours. But I answer, that suppose they sit but six moneths, one of these six will be long e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough for the worser sort by many circumstances, and the manner of proceedings, to understand each other, if they were not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore acquainted with their persons or Characters; and then have they the other five moneths to be corrupt in, with greater temptations of wickednesse, then if they were to sit longer: First, because they have reason, according to their own interest, and the Proverb, <hi>to make hay whilest the Sun shines,</hi> especially those of the meaner sort, that have no other hopes, and nothing to lose: and there will be at once more reall causes for the delay of justice, and far better pretences; As first, the newnesse of businesse, which requires some time to be understood: And next, the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplicity, which will give them a very plausible pretence of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving severall complaints, together with a seeming zeale to dispatch all, though really to put off one businesse with another, by raising severall debates, and concluding nothing till the end of their Sessions, and so they may thrive by under-hand bribes that can never be proved against them, and leave the same busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesses to their Successors, who must be anew informed, and may play the same game over againe: So that it is evident there will be more reall causes of delay, and more temptations and excuses for corruption in a short, then a lasting Representative; and if so palpable an unjust sentence should be given, as would admit
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115042:6"/>of no interpretation or excuse, which seldome or never hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pens, who should punish them for it? Certainly, the next Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presentative would never (for their own sakes) make the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptnesse and insufficiency of their Jurisdiction so notorious, as to go beyond the ordinary method of a Repeal of the unjust act or sentence; or if they would proceed to punishment, they would scarce be able to execute it against a whole Representative with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a civill war, especially when halfe the old Assembly shall be sitting in this new one, to interrupt both the sentence and exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution of it; so that I thinke it sufficiently appears, that this changeable Councell is as uncontrouleable and otherwise more inconvenient then the perpetuall one: I am sure they may go to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with this note upon them, that every particular person in them hath a sufficient power to oppresse, but they must all joyn together to do a good turne, and then are very slowly and charga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to be drawne to it too; and for elective Kings, they are by our Adversaries own instance, as well as by the reasons already alledged, a remedy as bad as the disease of a forraigne Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment was to the Medes; so that our next refuge must be to a mixt Government for the redresse of our grievances, and if that failes us, we shall appeale to the people, and so come home againe: But to explaine the meaning of a mixt forme, I must except against the subordination either of King to Parliament, or Parliament to King; for where that is, the absolute ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary power so complained of on both sides, will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine in the Supreme, and so it cannot be properly a mixt Government; but it is to be termed mixt, when these two powers have either an equall Jurisdiction together, or by turnes to rule and call each other to an account, and either of these are very fine things in speculation; but ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solutely certain to be as inconsistent with all Order and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the practise, as it is for two Kings to reigne both toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in one Kingdome; for they will alwaies either really differ in opinion, or pretend to do so when any good thing is proposed by either, through envy, jealousie, ambition or interest; and so either there shall be no administration of Justice at all, or more certainly, an opposition with fire and sword; &amp; the like must cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly fall out where Rulers should take their turnes, for those
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115042:7"/>that have the advantage of possession, with the present power of obliging all ambitious, necessitated and covetous people, and the like advantage of ability to punish the rich and fearfull, shall be able to make good that wrongfull possession against the rightfull Successors, to the horrible confusion if not the ruine and desola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Nation, as we very well know by wofull experience; so that it is clear that no Countrey can be free, neither from in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conveniences in a civill Government, nor from the arbitrary power of a Militia, either in a King, a High Constable, a General, or something of that nature equally dangerous; without they will lye open both to invasions from abroad, and insurrections at home. But now let me come to that which our pretended lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of liberty would have to be the remedy to all these disorders, I mean appeales to the people; and I shall with confidence a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verre, that this remedy will at any time turn to all these diseases put together; and so the supposed cure of some few maladies, shall draw on the most endlesse and unexpressible miseries that can befall mankind in this world: and though I shall never deny that, the health of the people is the Supreme Law, yet, I must ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver allow them to be their own Physitians; and to make it the clearer we will suppose, though not grant, that the people chose the first Rulers: and the first question I shall aske is what the word Ruler or Governour signifies? doth it not imply the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding power of an absolute Judge, or at least a Judge of such rules as are given him; and can there be command without o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience, or is there obedience where there is contradiction, or any trust reposed without submitting to the reason and consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the Trustee? Can I command those that I have contracted with to command me, be Judge of my Judges? certainly no, all these are contrary to reason and conscience, and destructive to all commerce; and now behold the deluge that this popular power lets in. First it is evident that the people must assemble to judge together of the reasons that induce them to the necessity of their intended alteration of Governours; and if they are the Supreme Judges and have this liberty at one time, they have it likewise by the same reason at all times: and it is as certain, that a part of them must meet before they can all assemble; and by conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence, any faction of innovators, theefs, murtherers, and the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115042:7"/>like, may legally make use of this pretence to assemble for the spoil or destruction of their Countrey; and that they will do this is as certain as it is that there are a sufficient number of people in any Nation whatsoever, that would be glad of an opportunity of thriving wickedly; but admit this supposition to be false, and that they would never stir but upon a necessary occasion, and were all assembled, which is impossible, and should with one voice resolve on a reformation, when they once come to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars all must infallibly turne to discord. For the first of these learned proposers shall be sure to be contradicted as plausibly, be it right or wrong, by some of the more cunningly ambitious and necessitated amongst them, that dare venture at any thing, and care not what followes, so as they can by a learned speech set all on slame, and make themselves heads of factions, the better to sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfie their ravenous desires on the best of the flock. And so this reformation becomes a good beginning to the totall tearing out their own bowells by civill distension, and leaving the carkase of the Common-Wealth for a prey to a Forrainer. Here we see the undeniable effect of that Maxime of, all Government being fundamentally in the people; and indeed it had been strange, that all Government should have been in them that have no Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in them: And I confesse, if they had been the Governours, I do not know who had been left to have been governed. And therefore since this can be no Maxime at all, and that we must have a Government, and that all of them have their inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, I shall conclude with that which I have said before, that the will of one man, though never so corrupt, is to be satisfied and glutted without any extraordinary prejudice to a whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and he is more likely to have care of a Kingdome that is to leave it to his posterity, then he that hath onely his own being to provide for out of it, and can only forfeit his time by his mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanours, and run away with the publique wealth when his reigne is almost at an end. Besides, a hereditary King hath no need of an Army on foot to keep him in possession; and he hath much the advantage in an extraordinary care of his education, with the stock and example of all his heroick Ancestors, as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of doing nobly. Besides, a notable store of his Fathers lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and experienced Councellors, that can sufficiently informe
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115042:8"/>him of the hazard of governing ill, and would be able to steer his affaires, if the worst should happen, that he should be left a child or prove a foole; since there is no question, but the wiser sort would know better then the fools, how to humour him, and keep still in his favour. But howsoever, these inconveniences are mortall and uncertain; but those of any popular or elective Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment certain and endlesse: and no doubt, if there were any Government in the world that were infallible, it would have been found out by this time, and all people would have both flown to it, and stuck to it. But it is evident, that when we have done all we can, we must trust God with somthing: his providence wil govern that world which it hath created. And we see that both that divine will, and the wisdom of the greatest part of the world in all ages to this day have (by the practice of it) confirmed heredi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary Monarchies to be the best.</p>
               <p>And now I shall wind up all with the confutation of our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines last assertion, that Antimonarchicalnesse is no crime at all, and that they that chuse may change. I think I have already shewed the inconveniences of this allegation; but for the inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice of it I shall only aske, whether they that give any thing may take it away again when they please? and whether a Theef deserves hanging for a robbery or no? And if that be the reward for a private robbery by the Lawes of our own and other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, what will then the publike Murtherers and Theefs deserve, that not onely murther and rob their Prince of an inheritance, with the Revenue belonging to it, lineally devolved unto him from before the Norman Conquest, and since confirmed by his Subjects in Arms at the signing of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> when they were in full power to vindicate their Liberties, and therefore can have no shadow of a pretence to claime a greater liberty then they then reserved to themselves at that voluntary agreement, ratified then, and since confirmed by so many Oaths of Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, voluntary Protestations, and the like? but have robbed the universall people of a Prince so eminent in all the vertues ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaining to that publike condition, under whom they had so <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ong securely flourished, notwithstanding some petty grievances <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>prung from the corruption and mis-information of inferiour Ministers, which were all redressed, and the Authors offered to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115042:8"/>a legall triall, before the two Houses begun that quarrell with him, for betraying his trust, for which he now died contrary to the will of those Houses, who were an excellent constitution whilest they were free, and within their bounds of representing grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances, and preparing lawes, but are indeed as imministeriall dispensers of Justice, as those who contrary to their trust, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take from their servants to become their Judges, and the whole Kingdomes besides, to the present oppression, and future confusi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion and desolation of this flourishing Kingdome, if they do not speedily seek (by the offer of an honorable and well-grounded peace) to make reparation to that excellent Son our naturall Prince, who is so much the Image of all his Fathers vertues, as well as person, that we need not doubt his burying all his resentments for the peace and welfare of his three Kingdomes, if they can resolve to trust him whom they have not so personally disob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>